So starting.
Okay, good morning. Today is January 14th, this is the 27th of
טבת. Tevet. My name is Dan Margulies and Solomon... Rabbi Eleazer is
in Maryland. And we are in מסכת שבועות, Masechet Shavuot, the seventh
chapter, and we will pick up something like four-ninths of the way
down מו: עמוד ב, Mem Vav Amud Bet, where the גמרא Gemara
introduces us to the case of נחבל כיצד. Nichbal Keitzad. The משנה
Mishna had mentioned that in a case of a person taking... who
is injured, there is a potential for them to take a שבועה
דרבנן Shvua DeRabbanan to collect their damages, and the משנה Mishna explains
נחבל כיצד היו מעידים אותו שנכנס תחת ידו שלם ויצא חבול. Nichbal
Keitzad hayu mei'idim oto shenichnas tachat yado shaleim veyatza chavul. So two
witnesses testify that a person walked into a room with somebody else
uninjured and that when he left the room he was injured, but
nobody actually saw the attack.
So what happens? ואמר לו חבלת בי, Ve'amar lo chavalta bi, he
accuses the person of having injured him,
והוא אומר לא חבלתי, Vehu omer lo chavalti, and then the person
denies it. הרי זה נשבע ונוטל. Harei ze nishba venotel. So the
person who was injured can take a שבועה, Shvua, this is the
דרבנן DeRabbanan שבועה, Shvua, like we've been discussing the whole פרק, Perek,
and collect the damages. Just as a reminder, something I said yesterday
on שבת, Shabbat, it's not in the recording, but it's worth noting,
is that the entire principle of נשבע ונוטל, Nishba venotel, the דרבנן
DeRabbanan שבועה Shvua that enables a person to make a claim and
collect on that claim even without proof, goes against the fundamental דאורייתא
De'oraisa principle המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya, that fundamentally
whoever wants to collect on something has to bring proof. Here, in
lieu of proof, the Rabbis enabled you to take a שבועה Shvua
to collect in cases where they were concerned that people would otherwise
lose out. So all of these cases are somewhat unique in
comparison to most of דיני ממונות. Dinei Mamonot. So the גמרא Gemara
says נחבל כיצד, Nichbal Keitzad, what case must we be talking about?
So the משנה Mishna had already explained what נחבל Nichbal meant. It
sounds perhaps like there was a very early text of the משנה
Mishna which just listed the cases, then a later text of the
משנה Mishna came to explain what those cases were, and now the
גמרא Gemara is elaborating further. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רב
יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
quoted his teacher שמואל, Shmuel, לא שנו אלא במקום שיכול לחבל בעצמו.
Lo shanu ela bemakom sheyachol lachabel be'atzmo.
This הלכה Halacha was only taught regarding a circumstance where it would
have been possible for the person to injure himself, so the שבועה
Shvua is to clarify that he didn't injure himself, but in fact
is claiming that he was injured by this other person. אבל במקום
שאינו יכול לחבל בעצמו נוטל שלא בשבועה. Aval bemakom she'eino yachol lachabel
be'atzmo notel shelo bishvua. In a case where it would be impossible
for him to have been injured on his own, that is, the
only logical conclusion would be that the other person injured him, then
he can collect even without taking the שבועה. Shvua. That is, the
שבועה Shvua still has to serve some level of proof or some
level of confirmation of the truth, but in a case where it
would be totally impossible for this person to have been injured in
any other way, then the שבועה Shvua is unnecessary. The גמרא Gemara
asks וניחוש דילמא בכותל נתחבט, Venichush dilma bekotel nitchabet, maybe he got
cut on the wall? So it's still possible that even if a
person couldn't injure himself, you know, punching himself in the stomach or
something like that, but it could be that you scraped against the
wall, you got cut on a rock, something like that. That is,
walking into this room, just because the other person was in the
room doesn't mean you were injured by them. So the גמרא Gemara
answers תני רבי חייא, Tani Rabbi Chiyya, there's a teaching from רבי
חייא, Rabbi Chiyya, שעלתה לו נשיכה בגבו ובין אצילי ידיו, She'alta lo
neshicha begavo uvein atzilei yadav, that the injury was either on... he
was bitten on the back or it was an injury on his
elbow, he was bitten on the elbow perhaps, so that a place
where it would be impossible, number one, impossible for him to have
been injured himself in that way and it would have been impossible
for him to have been injured by the wall in that way,
so it must be that it was an injury caused by another
person. ודילמא אחרי, Ve'dilma acher, maybe it was another person, that is,
not the accused but some third party who we were otherwise unaware
of?
ודילמא אחרי עבד ליה, Ve'dilma acher avid leih, maybe somebody else did
it to him? דליכא אחרי, Delika acher, it must be in a
case where we have evidence or we have proof that there was
no other person there. So, conclusion of this point is that for
a נחבל Nichbal to take a שבועה, Shvua, it must be number
one that the injury was something that he could have done to
himself but... but that there was no other person there and it's
a type of injury that is obviously caused by a human being,
not something that could have been caused by rubbing against the wall
or some inanimate object. So we have proof that it must have
been either he injured himself or this other person injured him and
he can take the שבועה Shvua to confirm that it must have
been the other person who injured him and it wasn't that he
injured himself. Okay, now we get into the... The main meat of
our דף daf today, which is the question the topic of וכשכנגדו
חשוד על השבועה. ukesheknegedo chashud al hashvu'ah. What if the opposing party
in your case, the other litigant is suspect of taking a שבועה?
shvu'ah? That is, under normal circumstances I would be in a case
against David and in this case David would take the שבועה, shvu'ah,
but let's say for whatever reason David is unable to take the
שבועה shvu'ah because he's suspect. So then the שבועה shvu'ah reverts back
at the דרבנן derabbanan level to me. That is, we would normally
have a case. ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon are in a court
case together and ראובן Reuven would have to take a דאורייתא שבועה.
d'Oraisa shvua So instead ראובן Reuven can't take the שבועה, shvu'ah. so
שמעון Shimon takes a דרבנן derabbanan שבועה shvu'ah, instead. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says וכשכנגדו חשוד, ukesheknegedo chashud, the person opposite
him in the case is suspect, ואפילו שבועת שוא, va'afillu shvu'at shav,
even someone who's suspect of having sworn falsely on שבועת שוא. shvu'at
shav. שבועת שוא, shvu'at shav, we should note, unlike שבועת העדות shvu'at
ha'edut and שבועת הפקדון, shvu'at hapikkadon, שבועת שוא shvu'at shav is not
a monetary שבועה. shvu'ah So let's see. So the גמרא Gemara says
מאי אפילו שבועת שוא, mai afillu shvu'at shav, what does it mean
even a שבועת שוא? shvu'at shav? לא מבעיא קאמר לא מבעיא הנך
דאית בהו כפירת ממון, la mibba'ya ka'amar la mibba'ya hanch de'it behu
kfirat mamon,
we're not only saying that this applies to a kind of a
if you're suspect about swearing falsely for שבועות shvu'ot regarding denial of
a monetary claim, אלא אפילו הא נמי דכפירת דברים בעלמא הוא, ella
afillu ha nammi dekfirat devarim be'alma hu, but even for שבועת שוא
shvu'at shav which is a denial of a you've been shown to
swear falsely even for something which is which only undermines your verbal
reliability, your trustworthiness, even if it wasn't in a case where you
were denying a monetary claim.
Okay. לא מהימן, la meheiman, he wouldn't be believed. וליתני נמי שבועת
ביטוי, u-litni nammi shvu'at bittui, so why doesn't the משנה Mishnah mention
שבועת ביטוי? shvu'at bittui? Because שבועת שוא shvu'at shav is just 'oh
I swore that a rock is a piece of gold' or something
like that, or I said something false and I swore about it.
But שבועת ביטוי shvu'at bittui could be 'I swear I'm going to
go on vacation to Bermuda' and then I end up not going.
So what kind of why wouldn't the משנה Mishnah mention שבועת ביטוי
shvu'at bittui as well? That's a similar type of untrustworthy person, someone
who'd be swearing falsely about and is just a not someone who
tells the truth necessarily. So the גמרא Gemara says כי קתני שבועה
דכי קא משתבע בשקרא קא משתבע. ki katni shvu'ah de-chi ka mishtava
beshikra ka mishtava. When you take a שבועת שוא shvu'at shav you
know in the moment that you're lying.
אבל שבועת ביטוי דאיכא למימר דבקושטא קא משתבע, aval shvu'at bittui de'ika
lemeimar de-bekushta ka mishtava, it's possible for שבועת ביטוי shvu'at bittui to
be in the moment that I intend to fulfill the שבועה. shvu'ah.
When I took the שבועה shvu'ah. I meant to go on vacation
but then a few months later happened that I it turned out
that I was unable to get the money together or something. So
I'm liable for having sworn falsely, but at the time I took
the שבועה shvu'ah I intended to keep it. לא קתני, la katni,
so we don't mention שבועת ביטוי shvu'at bittui because it's not a
perfect comparison because not every case of שבועת ביטוי shvu'at bittui is
going to be an indication that the person is a liar or
that the person is known to swear falsely necessarily. Even if you
end up breaking a שבועת ביטוי shvu'at bittui you're not necessarily a
liar. Okay. תינח אוכל ולא אוכל. tinach ochal velo ochal. That makes
sense if you say that the person violated a שבועה shvu'ah about
the future. אכלתי ולא אכלתי מאי איכא למימר? achalti velo achalti mai
ika lemeimar? But does it really true regarding שבועת ביטוי shvu'at bittui
about something that happened in the past? If I said I took
a שבועה shvu'ah 'I went on vacation to Bermuda', then when I
take the שבועה shvu'ah I know whether or not I'm telling the
truth.
תנא שבועת שוא וכל דדמי ליה. tanna shvu'at shav ve-chol dedami leh.
So when the תנא Tanna said, that is when the משנה Mishnah
said שבועת שוא, shvu'at shav, it means everything comparable to שבועת שוא.
shvu'at shav. And רש''י Rashi says in two words,
כל דדמי, kol dedami, three words, כל שבועה לשעבר. kol shvu'ah lesha'avar.
Every שבועה shvu'ah that applies to the past. That is when you
take a שבועה shvu'ah about something that happened in the past, that
is either שבועת שוא shvu'at shav or part of the cases of
שבועת ביטוי, shvu'at bittui, they could be referring to things which in
the moment you knew whether they were true or not. And therefore,
if you're חשוד chashud about those, that is if you regularly or
perhaps even only once violate those type of שבועות shvu'ot and it's
confirmed that you've violated them and you've been punished for it or
whatever, then at that point you become someone who's חשוד על השבועה,
chashud al hashvu'ah, we're suspect that you don't swear truthfully and therefore
the you we wouldn't allow you to take a שבועה shvu'ah in
court, so the שבועה shvu'ah will switch over to the other litigant.
How does one prove that a person made a שבועת שוא? shvu'at
shav? I mean how would you prove that somebody heard it I
guess or something.
Yeah, or something, I mean otherwise he wouldn't have had to bring
a קרבן, korban, he wouldn't right, any of those everything that we
did in the third and fourth and fifth and sixth.
These שבועות shvu'ot are not getting related to litigation though.
No, exactly. Right. These are שבועות shvu'ot that take place out of
court. That's what's interesting about it, is that the משנה Mishnah had
pointed out that someone who's חשוד על השבועה chashud al hashvu'ah even
for an interpersonal or or a factual type of שבועה, shvu'ah שבועת
שוא, shvu'at shav, שבועת ביטוי, shvu'at bittui, if if you've been shown
to To swear falsely in those circumstances, then you're liable, then you're
suspect even to take שבועות shvuos in court as well. And therefore
we don't let you take the שבועה. shvu'ah, We're right at the
top of דף מ"ז עמוד א' Daf Mem Zayin Amud Aleph and
the first line, continuing an explanation of the משנה. Mishna. The משנה
Mishna had said היה אחד מהם משחק בקוביא. Haya echad mehem mesachek
bekubya. The משנה Mishna had said, and what if one of the
litigants is a dice player or someone, right, the משנה Mishna listed
many examples, a gambler.
Sorry, it was right... the משנה Mishna continued toward the... sorry...
on the top of מ"ה עמוד א', Mem Hey Amud Aleph, the
משנה Mishna said היה אחד מהם משחק בקוביא. Haya echad mehem mesachek
bekubya. If one of them was a gambler. מלווה בריבית Malve beribit
or someone who lends money with interest. ומפריחי יונים, U'mafrichei yonim, someone
who is a dove keeper who gets involved with other people's doves
and all things like that. וסוחרי שביעית V'socharei shevi'is or someone who
sells the produce of the שמיטה Shmita year. שכנגדו נשבע ונוטל. Shekenegdo
nishba v'notel.
So such people as well, we don't allow them to take the
שבועה shvua. and the שבועה shvua reverts even a case of שבועה
דאורייתא, shvua d'oraisa, the שבועה shvua reverts to the other litigant who
takes a שבועה דרבנן, shvua d'rabbanan, נשבע ונוטל. nishba v'notel. So the
גמרא Gemara asks: היי תו למה לי? Hai tu lama li? Why
do we have to mention all of these cases? So תנא פסולי
דאורייתא וקתני פסולי דרבנן. Tana pesulei d'oraisa v'katani pesulei d'rabbanan. Because the
משנה Mishna wanted to list first a פסול דאורייתא psul d'oraisa that
is חשוד על השבועה, hashud al hashvua, someone who violates שבועת שוא
shvuas shav is someone who's disqualified themselves at the דאורייתא de'oraita level
from taking שבועות. shvuos. And gamblers and people like that are people
who the rabbis created this category of a דרבנן פסול. d'rabbanan psul.
It's interesting, usually we think of these people as a פסול עדות.
pasul eidus. They're disqualified from testifying. Here we see that such people
are also disqualified from swearing. Someone asked yesterday, what's the difference between
the requirements for someone to take an oath and someone to testify
in court? We see that they play different roles, but here because
we're talking about reliability, believability, it sounds like they would have comparable,
comparable criteria. So it's interesting to see that.
I didn't know
there were any different criteria. Well, the main difference would be that,
what was asked yesterday, is that women can't be witnesses on a
monetary case unless both parties agree to it, but in the case
of שבועות shvuos obviously women would be involved in taking שבועות shvuos
because they could be litigants all the time. So that's sort of
one of the main qualifications that would be different. Maybe the only
one.
But you can't, if you're פסול pasul for a שבועה shvua and
you take a שבועה shvua and violate it, no consequences? Meaning what?
But this is again, this is the court imposing a שבועה. shvua
So you imagine what? That a person comes to court...
no no, well let's say it's out of court though.
But out of court you wouldn't take this שבועה. shvua. This is
a שבועה shvua. that the judges tell you to take to resolve
a court case.
Okay, well you can ask later.
Okay, so היו שניהם חשודים. Hayu shneihem hashudim. The משנה Mishna had
then addressed a case, well what if both of them are חשוד?
chashud? What if neither of these parties can take a שבועה? shvua
That is, we have a very interesting conclusion,
and the משנה Mishna had
said היו שניהם חשודים חזרה השבועה למקומה, Hayu shneihem hashudim chazra hashvua
limkoma, דברי רבי יוסי. divrei Rabbi Yossi. The שבועה shvua? returns to
its place. We're going to see there's a מחלוקת, machlokes, what does
that mean? That's רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yossi opinion. ורבי מאיר אומר, V'Rabbi
Meir omer, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says: יחלוקו, yachloku, they just split
it. יחלוקו Yachloku should remind us of course of the first משנה
mishna in בבא מציעא Bava Metzia and the
opinion
of סומכוס, Sumchus, the opinion we've seen in a variety of places.
These are, excuse me if I'm...
סומכוס... Sumchus... מכות, Makkos, right, you get kicked out of ישיבה yeshiva
for saying stuff like that. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says: אמרה
ליה רבא לרב נחמן, Amrah lei Rava l'Rav Nachman, רבא Rava asked
רב נחמן: Rav Nachman: So היכי תנן? Heichi tnan? What's taught in
our משנה? mishna? אמר ליה לא ידנא. Amar lei lo yadna. I
don't, meaning, meaning which opinion do we follow from the משנה? mishna?
And he says I don't know.
הלכתא מאי? Hilchesa mai?
What's the פסק? psak?
My question always. Right.
הלכתא מאי? Hilchesa mai? And then רבא Rava said: Okay, I'm going
to ask you a more clarified question. What's the הלכה? halacha? אמר
ליה לא ידנא. Amar lei lo yadna. רב נחמן Rav Nachman said
he doesn't know. What's interesting of course, we know רב נחמן Rav
Nachman to be very... רב נחמן Rav Nachman knows דינים dinim very
well. So this must have been an earlier stage of רב נחמן's
Rav Nachman career because now we hear a confirmation of how רב
נחמן Rav Nachman פוסק paskens later.
I'm sorry, so what's the difference between the first question and the
second one, היכי תנן Heichi tnan and הלכתא מאי? Hilchesa mai?
היכי תנן Heichi tnan sounds like something more along the lines of
in a theoretical sense whose opinion in the משנה mishna should we
follow? We have a מחלוקת machlokes between רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and
רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, who do we follow?
And הלכתא מאי? Hilchesa mai?
I thought it was like, you know, who's the what, right?
In other words, do we have a... who says what? Maybe it's
who says what. There's some lack of clarity in רב נחמן's Rav
Nachman mind about this משנה. mishna. But now later we have confirmation
that רב נחמן Rav Nachman follows the opinion of רבי יוסי. Rabbi
Yossi. So what do we see? איתמר אמר רבי יוסי בר מניומי
אמר רב נחמן. Ismar amar Rabbi Yossi bar Minyumi amar Rav Nachman.
So רבי יוסי בר מניומי Rabbi Yossi bar Minyumi quoted רב נחמן
Rav Nachman as having said: רבי יוסי אומר יחלוקו. Rabbi Yossi omer
yachloku. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi is the one who says יחלוקו. yachloku.
וכן תני רב זביד בר אושעיא: V'chein tani Rav Zvid bar Oshaya:
רבי יוסי אומר יחלוקו. Rabbi Yossi omer yachloku. We have another אמורא
Amora who says that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi is the one who
said יחלוקו. yachloku. איכא דאמרי תני. Ika d'amri tani. רב זביד אמר
רבי יהושע רבי יוסי אומר יחלוקו Rav Zvid amar Rabbi Yehoshua Rabbi
Yosei omer yachloku and there is another version of that מימרא memra
that also says that a different אמורא Amora says that רבי יוסי'ס
Rabbi Yosei's opinion is יחלוקו. yachloku. איכא דאמרי Ika d'amri and there
are those who say that even another version, sorry, I just read
that. אמר רב יוסף בר מניומי Amar Rav Yosef bar Minyumi and
רב יוסף בר מניומי Rav Yosef bar Minyumi said עבד רב נחמן
עובדא יחלוקו avad Rav Nachman uvda yachloku and רב נחמן Rav Nachman
actually dealt with the case in practice, he said יחלוקו. yachloku. So
whether that means that so it sounds like what that's saying is
number one רב נחמן Rav Nachman concludes the practical הלכה halacha is
יחלוקו yachloku and possibly the reason why he said that is because
רבי יוסי'ס Rabbi Yosei's opinion that he confirmed that that was רבי
יוסי'ס Rabbi Yosei's opinion not רבי מאיר'ס Rabbi Meir's opinion. So the
משנה Mishna may be flipped
and so in a מחלוקת machloket between רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei and
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir we would follow רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei that
would be the reason why. So that was maybe some of the
confusion earlier on was that רב נחמן Rav Nachman maybe didn't have
access to those other traditions about the text of the משנה Mishna
and was confused because we have a מחלוקת machloket between רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosei and רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Right, our text is different.
Our text says רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei is the one who says
חזרה שבועה למקומה hazra shvua limkomo and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said
יחלוקו yachloku which is why there was a question. Once these other
traditions seemingly at least some of them perhaps coming from yeah from
רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. If it's from רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua is in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael he may have
had a different version of the משנה Mishna that was brought to
בבל Bavel may have provided some confirmation for רב נחמן Rav Nachman
to conclude oh actually our text of the משנה Mishna needs to
be flipped or something like that that the הלכה halacha is יחלוקו.
yachloku. Okay, so now we have to parse what is this phrase
חזרה שבועה למקומה. hazra shvua limkomo. So להיכן חזרה? L'heichan hazra? What
does it mean that the שבועה shvua goes back? Where does it
go to? אמר רבי אמי Amar Rabbi Ami רבותינו שבבבל אמרו חזרה
שבועה לסיני. Raboteinu shebiBavel amru hazra shvua l'Sinai.
According to רבי אמי Rabbi Ami says סיני Sinai first, in other
words חזרה שבועה למקומה hazra shvua limkomo is the first opinion.
Right, but
now
because we've flipped it, right, that is רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei is
the one who said יחלוקו yachloku now so it sounds like רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir is the one who said חזרה שבועה למקומה. hazra
shvua limkomo. But we end up trying to פסקן pasken both
but we'll see what חזרה שבועה למקומה hazra shvua limkomo means. We'll
see. Okay, we're going to see it's a debate between
רבותינו שבבבל Raboteinu shebiBavel and רבותינו שבארץ ישראל. Raboteinu sheb'Eretz Yisrael. The
Rabbis of בבל Bavel and Rabbis of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael specifically
between רב ושמואל Rav u'Shmuel against רבי אבא. Rabbi Abba. Okay. So
אמר רבי אמי, Amar Rabbi Ami, רבי אמי Rabbi Ami said רבותינו
שבבבל אמרו חזרה שבועה לסיני. Raboteinu shebiBavel amru hazra shvua l'Sinai. The
שבועה shvua returns to סיני Sinai that is in the absence of
the שבועה shvua what would you do otherwise? You would treat this
as a normal case of theft or a normal case of damages
or anything else and without proof you can't do anything. That's what
חזרה שבועה לסיני hazra shvua l'Sinai sounds like it means.
רבותינו שבארץ ישראל אמרו חזרה שבועה למחויב לה. Raboteinu sheb'Eretz Yisrael amru
hazra shvua limchuyav lah. The שבועה shvua returns to the one who
was initially obligated to take the שבועה. shvua That is if it
were a case of a דאורייתא שבועה de-oraisa shvua then it would
be someone who would have been taking a שבועה shvua. to get
himself out of paying but since he can't take the שבועה shvua
then he has to pay. That is what like let's say I'm
trying to claim a loan and I say oh you lent me
100 dollars and I have עד אחד ed echad that testifies that
I lent him 100 dollars. So then and you say you don't
say anything. So what do you have against עד אחד? ed echad?
You have to take a שבועת עד אחד. shvuat ed echad. But
you're חשוד על השבועה hashud al hashvua so you can't take the
שבועה. shvua So the שבועה shvua. goes to me but I'm חשוד
על השבועה. hashud al hashvua. So the שבועה shvua returns to you
and now that you can't swear you have to pay me the
100 dollars. That is basically we resolve it would be resolving the
case as if the person had said when given the option swear
or pay they said okay I can't swear so I'm going to
have to pay. Okay. So that's what we would say חזרה שבועה
למחויב לה. hazra shvua limchuyav lah. That's what was said in ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Okay. So אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa, רב
פפא Rav Papa said רבותינו שבבבל רב ושמואל. Raboteinu shebiBavel Rav u'Shmuel.
When we see the phrase רבותינו שבבבל Raboteinu shebiBavel all across ש"ס
Shas we should know that it refers specifically to רב ושמואל. Rav
u'Shmuel. And רבותינו שבארץ ישראל Raboteinu sheb'Eretz Yisrael when we see the
reference to our Rabbis in Israel that's רבי אבא. Rabbi Abba. Okay.
So רבותינו שבבבל Raboteinu shebiBavel and now we're going to see
specifically cases with both רב ושמואל Rav u'Shmuel and רבי אבא Rabbi
Abba in reference to this הלכה, halacha, the הלכה halacha of חזרה
שבועה למקומה. hazra shvua limkomo. What does חזרה שבועה למקומה hazra shvua
limkomo mean playing out with the opinions of רב ושמואל Rav u'Shmuel
and רבי אבא. Rabbi Abba. Proof that each of them holds the
opinion that has already been attributed to them. Okay, so now we're
going to see that. So we
say רבותינו שבבבל רב ושמואל דתנן Raboteinu shebiBavel Rav u'Shmuel d'tenan because
we have this משנה וכן היתומים לא יפרעו אלא בשבועה. Mishna v'chein
hayetomim lo yifra'u ela b'shvua. So orphans shouldn't pay back their
loans except if they take a שבועה. shvua והוינן בה, V'havinan bah,
there was a מחלוקת machloket about this.
מן? Man? What שבועה? shvua. What are you talking about? Like what
case is this? So אילימא מלווה הוון שקיל בלא
שבועה. ee'leima malveh havun shakal b'lo shvua. If their father was a
borrower so he took the money without having to take a שבועה
shvua? ואינהו בשבועה v'inhu b'shvua and they should have to pay it
back with a שבועה? shvua It doesn't make sense. אלא הכי קאמר,
ela hachi ka'amar, this is how we should understand this משנה. mishna.
וכן היתומים מן היתומים לא יפרעו אלא בשבועה. vechein hayetomim min hayetomim
lo yifre'u ela bishvua.
If witnesses are paying back a loan to other I'm sorry, if
orphans are paying back a loan to other orphans, they should only
pay it back with a שבועה. shvua? רב ושמואל דאמרי תרווייהו, Rav
uShmuel de'amri tarvaihu, רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel both agree, לא שנו
אלא שמת מלווה בחיי לווה. lo shanu ela shemet malve bechaye loveh.
That's only if the borrower had died during the lifetime of the
lender. אבל מת לווה בחיי מלווה, aval met loveh bechaye malve, but
if the lender died in the lifetime of the borrower, כבר נתחייב
מלווה לבני לווה. kevar nitchayev malve livne loveh.
The borrower has already been obligated, at the time that the lender
dies, the debt is still transfers to his estate. It goes to
the לווה loveh's יורשים. yorshim. They can inherit the debt. So that's
not a problem. The problem is what if the borrower died during
the terms of the loan? So someone went and borrowed money and
then they were going to pay it back in the next two
years and then they died. So now their descendants inherit the money
and the
obligation, the liability, hasn't yet formally transferred because the terms
of the loan were not between the descendants with the lender. Okay,
so that's what's the problem. Okay. אבל מת לווה בחיי מלווה כבר
נתחייב מלווה לבני לווה. aval met loveh bechaye malve kevar nitchayev malve
livne loveh. שבועה. shvua. Okay, what, yeah?
Wait, why haven't they inherited it? What difference does it make when
the loan ends?
Right, the point is who can do what for whom. So it
makes it at least easier for us to accept the fact that
the heirs can collect on a loan, that the debt owed to
the estate transfers ownership to the heirs. It's harder to claim that
the debt can be bequeathed by the father to his heirs to
pay back a loan, because a loan was an agreement between two
people. So the liability of the loan transferring from father to son,
let's say, is something at least harder for us to swallow than
the ability to collect on a loan would transfer. But there we
have both. But the point is that the case we're talking about
is a case where first the borrower died and then the lender
died. And now we have two sets of יורשים, yorshim, two sets
of יתומים. yetomim. And the point is they have to take a
שבועה shvua. when they pay back the loan, okay?
But what's the difference to make if he dies before the end
of the loan or dies while the loan, during the period when
the loan is still due, two years?
Oh no, that should be the same. But meaning he should pay,
no, I'm just saying that he has to pay back the loan
at the end of the term of the loan, meaning, whatever, I'm
assuming he's going to pay on time. We have a חזקה chazaka
people pay. No, no, no, there's no it's not necessary for this.
Okay. Okay. לא יפרעו אלא בשבועה. lo yifre'u ela bishvua. רב ושמואל
דאמרי תרווייהו. Rav uShmuel de'amri tarvaihu. So רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel
both said, לא שנו אלא שמת מלווה בחיי לווה, lo shanu ela
shemet malve bechaye loveh, that the מלווה, malve, the borrower, died during
the lifetime of the lender, אבל מת לווה בחיי מלווה, aval met
loveh bechaye malve, if the lender died during the borrower's lifetime, כבר
נתחייב מלווה לבני לווה. kevar nitchayev malve livne loveh. The debt had
transferred that the מלווה, malve, the borrower, is obligated to pay the
heirs of the lender. So כבר נתחייב מלווה לבני לווה שבועה. kevar
nitchayev malve livne loveh shvua.
He's obligated to take a שבועה shvua in paying it back. ואין
אדם מוריש שבועה לבנו. ve'ein adam morish shvua livno. But the שבועה
shvua cannot be inherited. You can't transfer a שבועה shvua that you're
required to take a שבועה, shvua you can't transfer that to your
heirs when you die, that they should have to take a שבועה
shvua, in your place. So רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel say, חזרה
שבועה למקומה hazra shvua limkoma מן חזרה שבועה לסיני, min hazra shvua
leSinai, that is, the שבועה shvua evaporates. In the absence of the
ability that the שבועה shvua should be taken by person X, if
such a person is unable to take the שבועה, shvua the שבועה
shvua, disappears. That's what רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel would say.
And therefore But why does it disappear?
The loan doesn't disappear, but the point is we adjudicate the case
as if there, as if we didn't have the confirmation of the
שבועה. shvua So if you look at what רש"י Rashi says,
in the רש"י, Rashi, אין אדם מוריש לבנו ממון שהוא מחויב עליו
שבועה. ein adam morish livno mammon shehu mitchayev alav shvua.
A person cannot bequeath to his heirs money that he owes a
שבועה shvua. for. אלמא הואיל והוא מחויב שבועה שלא התקבלתי חוב זה
alma ho'il vehu mitchayev shvua shelo hitkabelti chov zeh in a case
where he's obligated to take a שבועה shvua
to swear that I haven't received this payment of this loan, ויתומים
אין יכולים לישבע כן, veyetomim ein yecholim lishava kein, but the heirs
can't take such a שבועה. shvua אלא שלא פקדנו אבא. ela shelo
pikadnu abba. That
all they can say is that our father never told us that
he had accepted the loan. ואין זו השבועה המוטלת על אביהם. ve'ein
zo hashvua hamutala al avihem. But that's not the same שבועה shvua.
that their father would be obligated to take. That is, it's sort
of like a שבועת ספק shvua'at safek kind of problem, which is
that the heirs won't have a full knowledge of all of their
father's business dealings to an extent that they would be able to
take the שבועה shvua about whether or not they know for sure
that their father accepted
the...
No, in a case, it would transfer to the
heirs.
I owe $10,000 and then I'm poof, I die, and of course
the debt would remain. The question would be, because the debt remains
as part of the estate. The point is that
the שבועה shvua is an interpersonal obligation. As Khan said, it's something
you can't transfer from father to son in the same way because
the heirs lack the knowledge of the details of the relationship of
borrower and lender. There is an interpersonal aspect of being מלוה ולוה
malveh ve'loveh
besides just the financial aspect. It's something you see comes up in
מסכת קידושין, Masechet Kiddushin, in the second פרק, perek, there's a bit
of a discussion about these שבועות shvuos as well. So there are
some things there about these kind of concepts that it's an interpersonal
liability or relationship between them. Okay, so that was Rav and Shmuel's
opinion. Now, רבותינו שבארץ ישראל, Rabbosinu shebe'eretz Yisrael, רבי אבא. Rabbi Abba.
So now we have a case of רבי אבא Rabbi Abba that's
going to confirm to us that רבי אבא Rabbi Abba is the
one who says חזרה שבועה למקומה chasra shvuah limkomah means חזרה שבועה
למחויב לה. chasra shvuah limchuyav lah. It returns to the initial first
party who was liable in the שבועה, shvuah and since he can't
take the שבועה, shvuah, he has to pay. So what's the case
of that? That, perhaps we could say even a famous case of
נסכא דרבי אבא. nascha de'Rabbi Abba. We had it back
on דף ל"ב lamed bais in שבועות Shvuos and on דף ל"ג
lamed gimmel in בבא בתרא. Bava Batra. So it's an old friend.
So this is the case. דההוא גברא דחטף נסכא מחבריה. dehahu gavra
dechataph nascha michavrei.
Someone grabbed a piece of metal, a piece of silver from his
friend. אתא לקמיה דרבי אמי. ata lekamei de'Rabbi Ammi. יתיב רבי אבא
קמיה yativ Rabbi Abba kamei and רבי אבא Rabbi Abba was a
student of רבי אמי Rabbi Ammi was watching the case. So he
said: אייתי חד סהדא דמחטף חטף מיניה. aytei chad sahada de'mechataph chataph
minei.
He brought one witness that he had snatched it from him. That
is, one person seems to have stolen something and there was one
witness to it. It's only עד אחד. ed echad. אמר ליה, amar
lei, אין חטפי בדידי חטפי. in chataph bedidi chataph. But he said:
I did take it, but I took it because it was mine
originally.
He was stealing it back from the person who we might have
thought was the original owner. So אמר רבי אמי: amar Rabbi Ammi:
היכי לידיינו דייני להאי דינא? heichi ledayanu dayanai lehai dina? How can
we judges judge this case? נימא ליה: neima lei: זיל שלים, zil
shalem, ליכא תרי סהדי. leika trei sahadai. If we tell him to
pay, there are not two witnesses. ניפטריה, niftereih, איכא חד סהדא. ika
chad sahada. If we just let him off scot-free,
there is one witness that he snatched it. נימא ליה: neima lei:
זיל אישתבע. zil ishtava. Should we tell him go take a שבועה?
shvuah, Which should seem to be a reasonable thing because we have
עד אחד. ed echad. So in a case of עד אחד ed
echad you usually would want to take a שבועה, shvuah? that's a
שבועה דאורייתא. shvuah de'Oraisa. But כיון דאמר מחטף חטפי, keivan de'amar mechataph
chataph, because he said I snatched it, הוה ליה כגזלן. hava lei
k'gazlan. He's like a גזלן. gazlan. There's a lot of ink been
spilled about dealing with this question. Why does it say הוה ליה
כגזלן, hava lei ke'gazlan, he's like a גזלן, gazlan, not הוה ליה
גזלן, hava lei gazlan, he is a גזלן? gazlan? So that's an
interesting thing to explore. So אמר ליה רבי אבא, amar lei Rabbi
Abba, רבי אבא Rabbi Abba said back to teacher רבי אמי: Rabbi
Ammi: הוה מחויב שבועה ואין יכול לישבע. hava mechuyav shvuah ve'ein yachol
lishava.
He's someone who's obligated to take a שבועה, shvuah, שבועת עד אחד,
shvuas ed echad, but he cannot swear. וכל המחויב שבועה ואינו יכול
לישבע משלם. vechol hamechuyav shvuah ve'eino yachol lishava, meshalem. Everyone who is
obligated to take the שבועה shvuah, and cannot take the שבועה shvuah
has to pay. So that's proof that רבי אמי Rabbi Ammi says
חזרה שבועה למקומה chasra shvuah limkomah means חזרה שבועה למחויב לה. chasra
shvuah limchuyav lah.
It returns to the one who's obligated to it and therefore he
has to pay. So we have now proof of each of the
opinions. Rav and Shmuel think it means poof, the שבועה shvuah just
disappears and with it the liability, and רבי אבא Rabbi Abba from
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael saying that it means that they have to
pay.
I'm getting a little bit hung up on the orphans though. I
mean the whole reason is, in other words there is an obligation,
just, you know, we want to make extra special sure, because, which
obligation? In other words the whole borrower and the lender and then
the, and then if they're both orphans, right, then you need to
swear but you can't and therefore we go, it goes unpaid? It
just seems a bit unfair. The whole reason why we make the
orphan swear just for an extra level of security,
but we don't really think it was paid? I mean it might
have been paid, so why does this guy lose out? We know
there's still a document there.
Why should, no, the point is that there isn't any document. If
there would be a שטר shtar it would solve all the problems.
I think there's no שטר. shtar.
Even, even, you know, even if both parties are dead and it's
just the orphans looking for the orphans?
I would think so.
The impression I got was that
even with that, I thought
there was a שטר shtar in one of those cases.
The notes are saying in the
ArtScroll, no, the ArtScroll I'll have to see.
It may be
a discussion in the ראשונים, Rishonim, I'm not sure.
Certainly the way the cases are presented in the גמרא Gemara is
never simple bottom line. There's obviously much more to explore. And certainly
the case of נסכא דרבי אבא nascha de'Rabbi Abba in בבא בתרא
Bava Batra there's much material about. I imagine this
earlier... No, I'm
saying what do you
think?
I'm
saying צריך עיון.
Tzarich Iyun. I'm willing to say I don't know it well enough
right now to answer the question.
As far as I can
say if there was no שטר Shtar then like you know,
meaning, so there's no witnesses and there's no nothing? So what is
the- what is the- No,
it could be a מלווה על פה. Milveh Al Peh. They they
swore when they when they lent the money or whatever.
So there were witnesses?
There could be witnesses, yeah, but the point is that there's this
added level of- there's meant to be this added level of security
for the יתומים. Yesomim. Usually we would say the added level of
security is to protect the estate of יתומים, Yesomim, children who've inherited
property- I mean imagine they're children- so that they're you know they
need this money to support their livelihood until they get old enough
to earn a living and things like that. So the rabbis instituted
various things to protect them. So here it would seem like that
שבועה shvuah is meant to add a level of security to you
know with business dealings with יתומים. Yesomim. We saw that at the
end of בבא בתרא Bava Basra a lot.
So it could be such a case here as well. And then
you're dealing with the question of okay and in this case well
now we have יתומים Yesomim with other יתומים. Yesomim. So who are
we trying to protect? And that's sort of this question as well.
Right. So then why shouldn't it be whatever it was from the
very beginning?
Well that's what רב ושמואל Rav U'Shmuel say. That is if they're
חשוד על השבועה Chashud Al Ha'Shvuah the שבועה Shvuah poof up and
disappears. No, not חשוד. Chashud. No, the case we're talking about-
we're extrapolating from the opinion of רב ושמואל Rav U'Shmuel a case
where neither party can take the שבועה. Shvuah Then the שבועה Shvuah.
up and disappears. So too they would apply in a case of
חשוד על השבועה Chashud Al Ha'Shvuah that if two people are each
חשוד על השבועה Chashud Al Ha'Shvuah and they have a case with
each other the
שבועה Shvuah up and disappears. No what I'm saying is you know
I need to take a שבועה Shvuah then you need to take
a שבועה Shvuah and no one knows and then just let it
just be from the very beginning as if the borrower and and
and the lender were both alive and then you'd just collect without
a שבועה, Shvuah right?
Well but that's what they're saying is once it's orphans with other
orphans and neither party will be able to take a שבועה Shvuah,
because אין אדם מוריש שבועה לבניו, Ein Adam Morish Shvuah L'Vanav,
so then poof the שבועה Shvuah disappears.
Right, but then the implication was then therefore they're out the money.
But right?
Wasn't that- Who's out the money? Let's see. Wait one second.
The the- Whoever owed the money- Right,
doesn't have to pay because-
No, I'm saying the opposite that since I can't- I don't know,
you don't know, but we do know.
So try not to die while- but that's my understanding.
And otherwise why didn't you just say in other words they each
cancel it out otherwise if only you know then therefore-
Well so you like רבי אבא'ס Rabbi Abba's answer better. רבי אבא
Rabbi Abba would give your answer to רב ושמואל'ס Rav U'Shmuel's case.
We're going to see רבא Rava likes רבי אבא'ס Rabbi Abba's answer
as well. So let's continue with the גמרא. Gemara. Okay.
But the bottom line in that case there would be no further
obligation for either party, why? I think so.
That's my- from the question.
Right. I think so.
I think they just cancel each other out and just-
I'd have to check but that's what I think seems to be
the conclusion from that case according to רב ושמואל. Rav U'Shmuel. But
we're going to see the סוגיא Sugya continues that with רבא'ס Rava's
opinion. So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, כוותיה דרבי אבא מסתברא. Kevaseih De'Rabbi
Abba Mistabra. רבא Rava thinks רבי אבא'ס Rabbi Abba's answer makes a
better sense. That is in a case where you're מחויב שבועה Mechuyav
Shvuah but you can't take the שבועה, Shvuah the שבועה Shvuah, goes
back to the first party and and they have to pay without
the שבועה. Shvuah Okay.
דתני רבי אמי, De'Tani Rabbi Ami, שבועת ה' תהיה בין שניהם. Shvuas
Hashem Tihyeh Bein Sheneihem. So it's interesting that it's תני Tani with
רבי אמי. Rabbi Ami. רבי אמי Rabbi Ami is one of the
early אמוראים. Amoraim. It's interesting it says תני. Tani. So תני רבי
אמי. Tani Rabbi Ami. רבי אמי Rabbi Ami said in this מימרא,
Meimra, שבועת ה' תהיה בין שניהם, Shvuas Hashem Tihyeh Bein Sheneihem, that
they have to take a שבועה. Shvuah. Someone between them, there will
be a שבועה Shvuah. of God between them, ולא בין היורשים, V'Lo
Bein Ha'Yorshim, but not between inheritors, within heirs. So היכי דמי? Heichi
Dami? What case are we talking about? אילימא דאמר ליה, Ileima De'Amar
Lei, מנה דאבא ביד אביך. Maneh De'Abba Beyad Avicha. If someone comes
to court and says but your father borrowed a hundred dollars from
my father, okay? ואמר ליה חמישין אית ליה וחמישין לית ליה, V'Amar
Lei Chamishin Is Lei V'Chamishin Leis Lei,
and he says back he he paid back fifty and there's fifty
left to pay back, so מה לי הוא מה לי אבוה? Mah
Li Hu Mah Li Avuh? What's the difference between him and his
father? Meaning okay that's just a מודה במקצת Modeh B'Miktzas case between
two people, whether he says my father borrowed it from your father,
whether he says I borrowed it from you or whatever, it's the
same thing.
Meaning they should have
to swear- And you should take a שבועת מודה במקצת. Shvuas Modeh
B'Miktzas. אלא לאו? Ella Lav? Meaning
so that רבי אמי'ס Rabbi Ami's דרשה Drasha is that יורשים Yorshim
can't take a שבועה Shvuah in place of their ancestors. But wait
a second, this sounds like a case where יורשים, Yorshim, where the
children are dealing with a case about their parents where they would
take a שבועה. Shvuah אלא לאו? Ella Lav? So what case must
we be talking about? דאמר ליה מנה לאבא ביד אביך, De'Amar Lei
Maneh L'Abba Beyad Avicha, my father borrowed-
your father borrowed a hundred dollars from my father. So אמר ליה
חמישין ידענא, Amar Lei Chamishin Yadana, he says fifty I know about,
וחמישין לא ידענא, V'Chamishin Lo Yadana, and fifty I didn't know about.
That is- He only borrowed fifty,
that's- Either he only borrowed fifty and I never heard about the
other fifty or right, yeah basically is the claim of he only
borrowed fifty and
I'm- no because לא ידענא, Lo Yadana, it's I don't know about
it. Because לא ידענא... Lo Yadana... is once you don't know about
it you can't take a שבועת מודה במקצת. shvuas modeh be-miktzas. So
that's the prompt. So אי אמר בשלמא אביו כי האי גוונא מחייב.
ee amar bishlama aviv k'hai gavna mechayev.
So if we would say in such a case that in the
if the father were there he would have to take the שבועה,
Shvuah. איצטריך קרא למפטר גבי יורשים, itzrich kra l'miftar gabei yorshim, then
that's a case where the פסוק pasuk is coming to tell us
that the יורשים yorshim would not take the שבועה. shvua, אלא אי
אמרת אביו כי האי גוונא נמי פטור, ella ee amart aviv k'hai
gavna nami patur, if you would tell me that in such a
case the father would even be פטור patur because he said I
don't know, so קרא גבי יורשים למה לי, kra gabei yorshim lama
li, then why do I have a פסוק pasuk telling me about
יורשים? yorshim? So that's a proof for רבי אבא's Rabbi Abba position
that in a doubtful case or in a case like this, we
would say חזר שבועה למקומה, chazar shvua limkomah, that he would have
to pay without taking the שבועה. shvua. Okay. ורב ושמואל האי שבועת
ה' מאי קדרשי ביה? v'rav u-shmuel hai shvuas Hashem mai kadarshi bei?
So what did רב ושמואל...
Rav u-shmuel... wait sorry what was the meaning? So in the case
that if he said that I only know about 50, I don't
know about the other 50, then the יתום yosom would...
so then it's like a case of שבועת מודה במקצת, shvuas modeh
be-miktzas,
but they can't take the שבועה shvua. because they say I don't
know, so then... so he would... so he would take שבועת מודה
במקצת. shvuas modeh be-miktzas.
But he can't though.
No, if he doesn't know about it. Right, so that's the point.
So if... and that's what the top of of מ"ז ע"ב mem
zayin amud beis is saying. That is in a case, right, in
a case of if it were
אביו כי האי גוונא מחייב, aviv k'hai gavna mechayev, the case where
the father would be obligated to take a שבועת מודה במקצת, shvuas
modeh be-miktzas, then we need the פסוק pasuk to tell me that
the יורשים yorshim will not take the שבועה.
shvua No, but we know that no one's taking a שבועה shvua.
if he's פטור. patur. No, in the first case he would. In
the first case of 50, right,
50 אית ליה it lei ו-50 לית ליה. v-50 leit lei. Oh
okay. That 50 I know that 50 he borrowed and 50 he
didn't borrow. So in other words I'm saying he only borrowed 50.
If he says if he only borrowed 50, then you take שבועת
מודה במקצת shvuas modeh be-miktzas and you'd be... only have to pay
the 50. But if he said I don't know, then you can't
take a שבועה shvua about it because you don't know. So he
could either.
No, he doesn't know about it. Right. So that's the point. So
if... and in his case he would have to pay too?
Yeah. Okay.
But typically if he says he acknowledges the
50, right, and he pays the 50, and the 50 he doesn't
know about he takes מודה במקצת modeh be-miktzas on the second 50.
But if he doesn't know about it, if he says לא ידענא
lo yadana and he can't swear about it to say I don't
owe you the other 50...
because he doesn't know.
But isn't מודה במקצת...
modeh be-miktzas... no מודה במקצת modeh be-miktzas is you're כופר במקצת, kofer
be-miktzas, right? You admit half and you deny the other half. You
say I only borrowed 50 from you with surety so that you're
able to swear. Right. If he says I don't know if I
borrowed $100 from you, I know it was at least 50, you
can't take a שבועה shvua about that because you don't have any
surety.
What's the difference?
No, because that's a case where there wouldn't be any liability of
the שבועה דאורייתא shvua de-oraisa at all. If it were a שבועה
דאורייתא... shvua de-oraisa... see
there's two different kind of problems. There's a problem of oh I'm
חשוד על השבועה chashud al ha-shvua where I'm an unreliable person so
then we'll switch it to the other party. If it's a case
where the דאורייתא d'oraisa שבועה shvua can't even latch on because it's
a case of doubt, so then nobody else could take the שבועה
shvua either.
So if the other person were to say you borrowed 100 from
me, and he says I know about 50, I don't know about
the other 50, that wouldn't be מודה במקצת modeh be-miktzas because...
that's not מודה במקצת. modeh be-miktzas.
But in this case it's not? That's the distinction? Which case? If
one were to say you borrowed 100 from me, and he says
no I only borrowed 50.
Then he takes מודה במקצת modeh be-miktzas
because he's acknowledging the 50,
right, and he's denying the other 50.
But isn't he saying there I don't know about 50?
No, he's saying I know I only borrowed 50. Uh huh.
The שבועה shvua has to be I swear I borrowed 50 from
you.
Well what's he saying about the other 50?
He's denying it. That's the point.
But in this case he's saying I don't know about 50, there's
a distinction?
Right, לא ידענא lo yadana I don't know is a שמא, shema,
is a doubtful claim, is a maybe. Right. We say if you
make a maybe claim, maybe claim is not worth as much as
a...
yeah. There's a distinction between how he starts, how he structures his
words.
Yeah. It's very important. But meaning we assume the person is telling
the truth. That is saying maybe is different than saying yes and
no.
It's not just the structure of the words, these are יתומים, yesomim,
they don't have personal knowledge...
no so even if the original would be like that, and if
it would be יתומים yesomim then certainly. Right. So אלא אי אמרת
אביו כי האי גוונא נמי פטור, ella ee amart aviv k'hai gavna
nami patur, if you would have said about such a case that
the father would even be פטור, patur, that is the case that
we're talking about, a case of לא ידענא, lo yadana, he doesn't
know, קרא גבי יורשים למה לי, kra gabei yorshim lama li, so
that's a problem for רבי אמי Rabbi Ami which is that it
sounds like the case that you wanted to talk about is a
case that we wouldn't need this פסוק pasuk anyway. So רבי אמי's
Rabbi Ami דרשה drasha is not such a valuable דרשה, drasha, but
it at least reminds us of רבי אבא's Rabbi Abba position. So
anyway, okay. ורב ושמואל האי שבועת ה' מאי קדרשי ביה? v'rav u-shmuel
hai shvuas Hashem mai kadarshi bei? What did רב ושמואל Rav u-shmuel
even use that פסוק pasuk for at all? That is רבי אמי
Rabbi Ami at least has something that
he... He pays the amount that he admitted to, right? Yeah.
And that's what's interesting also, the beginning of בבא מציעא Bava Metzia
you see the case of הילך. Helach. הילך Helach is in a
case where he said
you owe me a hundred dollars and he says no I only
owe you fifty and here it is and now I'm paid up.
He gives it to him right at that moment. In a case
of הילך Helach you also don't take מודה במקצת Modeh b'miktzat because
the act of paying off the debt at that moment closes the
docket on the case and so he escapes the שבועה. shevua. So
that's also an interesting סוגיא. sugya. That's like בבא מציעא דף ג,
Bava Metzia Daf Gimmel, ג ד. Gimmel Daled. הילך Helach like
here it is, take it. Right. So it's a very interesting...
what's he taking the שבועה shevua on
the
fifty or is he now denier?
The שבועה shevua is about the part he's denying. The שבועה shevua
reinforces the denial of the claim at the דאורייתא d'Oraita level.
Right. Wait, who are we פוסק poskening like? That's what I want
to
know.
Wait, so it sounds to me that this whole piece concludes like...
like רבי אבא Rabbi Abba it sounds like and that רב ושמואל's
Rav uShmuel position because רבא Rava in בבל Bavel later sort of
seems to be rejecting רב ושמואל Rav uShmuel against... against רבי אבא.
Rabbi Abba. But we'll see. So רב ושמואל האי שבועת ה' מאי
קדרשי ביה? Rav uShmuel hai shevuat Hashem mai k'darshi bei? What did
רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel use the פסוק pasuk for? מיבעי ליה
לכדתניא, Mibaya leih l'kid'tanya, they need it to teach this ברייתא. baraita.
שמעון בן טרפון, Shimon ben Tarfon, which sounds like the son of
רבי טרפון, Rabbi Tarfon, I wasn't a hundred percent sure to look
up who he is exactly but I think he's the son of
רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon which is interesting he doesn't come up so
often. שמעון בן טרפון אומר שבועת ה' תהיה בין שניהם. Shimon ben
Tarfon omer shevuat Hashem tihiyeh bein shneihem.
So he says what does it mean the פסוק pasuk says God's
שבועה shevua has to be between them? מלמד שהשבועה חלה על שניהם.
Melamed she'hashevua chala al shneihem. That the שבועה shevua lands on both
of them. So what does that mean?
No, really, what does that mean?
I don't really have a good sense what he's trying to say
with that.
But there's a note
on שניהם, shneihem, right, yeah,
in רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot but it's I don't think it's
even so clear about explaining. It says if the defendant swears falsely
the plaintiff is well as he is subject to divine retribution. The
defendant for invoking God's name in vain and the plaintiff for his
negligence in entrusting his property to an unreliable individual, thus bringing about
the desecration of God's name.
Okay, it's possible. I'm not sure, I don't exactly think it fits
that... I'm not sure. It's a strange דרשה derasha and it's sort
of unclear to me what's being said by this דרשה. derasha. שבועת
ה' תהיה בין שניהם מלמד שהשבועה חלה על שניהם. Shevuat Hashem tihiyeh
bein shneihem melamed she'hashevua chala al shneihem. The שבועה shevua lands on
both of them. So I don't...
this sounds like from talking about a פיקדון pikadon there.
Well, right, this is the point, is that we're talking about שבועת
השומרים shevuat hashomrim in the פסוק, pasuk, right. Okay, so that's the
first teaching of שמעון בן טרפון Shimon ben Tarfon and now we're
talking about שמעון בן טרפון Shimon ben Tarfon we have a few...
another teaching of...
anyway, why are we bringing this in?
Why are we bringing this in? Because this דרשה derasha is what
רב ושמואל Rav uShmuel use the פסוק שבועת ה' תהיה ביניהם pasuk
shevuat Hashem tihiyeh beineihem and not like for רבי אמי's Rabbi Ammi
דרשה. derasha.
Okay. So שמעון בן טרפון אומר, Shimon ben Tarfon omer, שמעון בן
טרפון Shimon ben Tarfon said another thing...
מביני ולא מן היורש. Mibeini v'lo min hayoresh. Right.
So we... because רב ושמואל Rav uShmuel are doing an הלכתי halachic
point and he's trying to learn like sort of like a moral
point...
Some kind of maybe it's a moral point, I'm not even sure.
I don't, again, I'm willing to accept that what David said but
I'm not sure it's...
what did it talk about...
Yeah I know I saw תוספות, Tosafot, I'm just saying I
don't... I'm not convinced a hundred percent what it... you know, anyway.
שמעון בן טרפון אומר, Shimon ben Tarfon omer, so we have another
statement of שמעון בן טרפון. Shimon ben Tarfon. אזהרה לאוקיב אחר נואף
מנין? Azhara l'okeiv achar noef minayin? How do we know that there
is a prohibition in the Torah not only for adultery but for
some kind of adulterous prostitution? You look in רש"י, Rashi, אוקיב אחר
המנאף, okeiv achar hamnaef, נעשה
לו אפוטרופוס להרגיל לו נשים לניאוף,
na'aseh
lo
apotropus l'hargil lo nashim l'niyuf,
someone who hires someone to go find married women for him to
sleep with. It's like a pimp? Some kind of a pimp of
some kind. It's very... anyway. So שמעון בן טרפון Shimon ben Tarfon
says how do we know that that's included in the prohibition of
ניאוף? niyuf? So אזהרה לאוקיב אחר נואף מנין, azhara l'okeiv achar noef
minayin, תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, לא תנאף, lo tinaf, and it's... it
should be read as if לא תניאף, lo tanif, don't enable other
people to commit adultery, not only לא תנאף, lo tinaf, not to
commit adultery yourself. Okay. ותרגנו
באהליכם.
Vatargenu b'oholeichem.
Oops, he's just bringing all the מימרות memrot of שמעון בן טרפון.
Shimon ben Tarfon.
Basically, because this is like the only place where he gets mentioned.
So שמעון בן טרפון אומר: Shimon ben Tarfon omer: תרתם וגניתם באהלו
של מקום. tartem u'ganitem b'ahalo shel makom.
So in describing the מרגלים meraglim having come back on the דברים
פרק א Devarim perek aleph talking about the מרגלים... meraglim... so תרתם
וגניתם. tartem u'ganitem. You... you went exploring, רש"י Rashi says תרתם את
הארץ tartem et ha'aretz the מרגלים meraglim scouted out the land, וגניתם
את המקום שהשכין שכינתו
ביניכם, u'ganitem et hamakom she'hishkin shechinato beineichem, you drove away God's presence...
Right. Okay. And another דרושא *drasha* at the beginning of
דברים *Devarim*, עד הנהר הגדול נהר פרת
*ad
hanahar hagadol nehar perat*, that is the the land the Jewish commonwealth
will extend all the way north to the Euphrates River. So שמעון
Shimon בן טרפון אומר *Shimon ben Tarfon omer*, קרב לגבי דהינא *kerav
legabei dehina* ואידיהם *ve'ideihem* דבי רבי Rebbe ישמעאל תנא tanna *debei Rabbi
Yishmael tana* דהינא *dehina* thing, very דהינא *dehina* or no. I don't
know what that is.
What? דהינא *Dehina*?
What what's he saying?
So רש״י Rashi *Rashi* says קרב לגבי דהינא ואידיהם *kerav legabei dehina
ve'ideihem*, אם נגעת במשוח בשמן *im nagata bemashuach bashemen*,
if you touch something that was was anointed with the oil, תהא
גם משוח בנגיעתו *tehei gam mashuach b'negiato*. כלומר *Klomar*, פרת הוא קטן
משלוש נהרות *Perat hu katan mishalosh neharot*. The Euphrates is a small
the smaller river of other rivers of ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* also.
Right. דהינא *Dehina* and אידהן *Idahan* are the other rivers.
No, but what he's saying is at least the way they explain
it, קרב לגבי דהינא *kerav legabei dehina*, touch someone who has oil
on him and then ואידהין *ve'idahin*, you too of course,
ואידהין *ve'idahin* and you get the oil.
Right. So the so this is a basically smaller river but it's
nearly next to it so it gets וארץ ישראל *ve'Eretz Yisrael* so
it gets some of the glory of being near ארץ ישראל *Eretz
Yisrael*.
Something like that.
That's why it's called נהר הגדול נהר פרת *nahar hagadol nehar perat*.
It's called a great river even though it's a small river, but
it is a great river. So I'm not sure. It's very strange.
Some kind of a דרושא *drasha*. Okay. דבי רבי Rebbe ישמעאל תנא
*Debei Rabbi Yishmael tana*, so this school from רבי Rebbe ישמעאל *Rabbi
Yishmael* said עבד מלך כמלך *eved melech k'melech*.
The slave of a king is like the king, which in context
may be going back to references we had about שבועות shvu'ot *shavuot*
that that a king is not taken for testimony and things like
that or it may it may be talking about the נהר פרת
*nehar Perat* that the large river is still called great because it's
in service of of the land of Israel or something. Some strange
דרושות *drashot* here. I'm not really sure what to make of them.
Okay. והחנוני על פנקסו *Ve'hachenvani al pinkaso*. Have to set the record
straight.
I always thought
it was פנקסו *pinkaso*.
Ah, what's the Greek word? You and פינכסא *pinchesa* סומכוס *Sumchos*.
Oh come on. What what is the Greek word is is פינכס
*pinax*. Okay, פנקסו *pinkaso*, his
פינכס *pinax*.
Isn't that what what you get at the baseball game? Peanuts. No.
It's a folding, so here, I'll do my best attempt at drawing
today.
This was what they had before they had cheap paper was they
had a thing like this, which was a wooden thing, and they
would pour wax
in
here
and then you can use a stylus to write in the wax,
and then when you're done you want to erase everything you just
melt down the wax again and smooth it flat. So that's a
פנקס *pinkas*. It's like a wooden board with wax on it. Okay.
פנקסו *Pinkaso*. Going to get kicked out of ישיבה *yeshiva* for saying
stuff like this.
No, it's the right word.
It's the right word, but the problem is because in Hebrew you
would never say a word like that because because because it should
there should be a שוא *shva* in the second letter. So that's
where you get פנקסו *pinkaso*, right?
Right?
But we can correct. So it's פנקס *pinax*
because the ק ס *kof samech* right is is is from Greek.
So okay.
And did they actually keep such a thing for ledgers typically?
Yeah, for sure. It was a was the normal writing writing book.
Because it wouldn't use paper.
Because paper was expensive. This is reusable, right? It's like a tablet.
You can you can you can keep track of your things for
today, you know, who came in and bought and sold and everything.
And then at the end of the day you don't need records
of that stuff. Maybe a couple things you write down, you know,
your your net for the day you'll write down on a paper
and then you'll just erase for tomorrow or whatever. Okay. So והחנוני
על פנקסו *Ve'hachenvani al pinkaso*. So what did the משנה mishna. *Mishna*
say about חנוני על פנקסו chanvani al pinkaso, *chenvani al pinkaso*? The
משנה mishna, *Mishna* had said that this is another case of a
שבועת דרבנן *shvuat d'rabanan*.
So if you go back to מ״ה עמוד א׳ *Mem Heh Amud
Aleph* to see the משנה mishna *Mishna*.
It's a bit farther down, right?
Oh no, it's towards the top. Like six lines down on מ״ה
עמוד א׳ *Mem Heh Amud Aleph*. והחנוני על פנקסו כיצד *Ve'hachenvani al
pinkaso keitzad*? What's this case? לא שיאמר לו כתוב על פנקסי שאתה
חייב לי מאתים זוז *Lo sheyomar lo katuv al pinkasi she'atah chayav
li matayim zuz*. It's not that he could say, oh, it's written
down in in my ledger that you owe me two hundred זוז
*zuz*, so you have to pay me and I can take a
שבועה shvu'ah *shvua* and collect on it. That would be totally unfair
because then every shopkeeper would just write down in his ledger that
people owe him money and go to court and swear and get
a lot of money. אלא אומר לו תן לבני סאתים חטין *Ella
omer lo ten livni satayim chitin*. Someone made a deal with the
shopkeeper and said, go, my son is going to come by later.
Give him, you know, two hundred, two סאה *se'ah* of wheat. תן
לפועל *Ten lapoel*... pay my workers this much money.
הוא אומר נתתי,
hu
omer
natati, they both agree that he gave them money.
Right. And they say, הוא אומר נתתי, he says, I gave it,
והן אומרים לא נטלנו, v'hein omrim lo natalnu, and they say we
never claimed it. So, הוא נשבע ונוטל, hu nishba v'notel, so he
has to take a שבועה shvu'ah to collect the money, והן נשבעים
ונוטלים, v'hein nishba'im v'notlin, and they can take a שבועה shvu'ah and
collect, that is, וחנוני v'chanvani and the, the claimants can all of
them take a שבועה shvu'ah against a בעל הבית ba'al habayit and
the בעל הבית ba'al habayit loses out. Basically, if you make a
deal like this in advance, make sure to keep the receipt, keep
track, because otherwise you're going to end up losing. Okay, so תני
אמר רבי, tani amar Rebbe, טורח שבועה זו למה? torach shvu'ah zo
lamah? Why, why do we have this שבועה shvu'ah? at all? רבי
Rebbe's asked.
אמר
ליה רבי חייא בר אבא
amar lei Rabbi Chiya bar
Abba
meaning, so רש״י Rashi says ששניהם באים לבית דין שתצא שבועה שוא
ביניהם she'shneihem ba'im l'veit din she'teitzei shvu'at shav beineihem because as is
mentioned in the beginning of בבא מציעא, Bava Metzia,
somebody is
lying, right?
If somebody exactly, כיצד אלו ואלו באים לידי שבועת שוא? keitzad elu
v'elu ba'im lidei shvu'at shav? Exactly. That was a משנה. Right.
From, from
רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, some
people say Ben Nanas.
Oh, Ben Nanas, right. Yeah. So, the opinion of Ben Nanas is,
is what's the point of this case? In this case, somebody is
lying, right? Either the חנוני chanvani is lying or the, or the
פועלים po'alim are lying.
Because if he says, if he says I paid them and they
say we never got paid, obviously someone is lying. Okay.
So Rebbe is asking, טורח שבועה זו למה לי? torach shvu'ah zo
lamah li? Why do we make people take a שבועה? shvu'ah Something
like Ben Nanas, it's a little bit different, but רש״י certainly connects
it to
Ben Nanas. So, טורח שבועה זו למה לי? torach shvu'ah zo lamah
li? אמר רבי חייא בר
אבא amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba תנינא שניהם נשבעים ונוטלים מבעל הבית.
tanina shneihem nishba'im v'notlim miba'al habayit. So if we say שניהם נשבעים
ונוטלים, shneihem nishba'im v'notlim, everybody takes a שבועה shvu'ah. and collects, so
what does it mean?
So are we talking about a case from the בעל הבית, ba'al
habayit, do we say קיבלה מיניה או לא קיבלה מיניה? kiblah minei
o lo kiblah minei? Did he receive it from him or not?
That is, מיניה, minei, is that the הלכה, halacha, right?
That once רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya told רבי Rebbi this answer, did,
did רבי agree to him or not? Okay,
so תא שמע, ta shema, so we have a ברייתא braita to
try to clarify. דתניא, d'tanya, רבי אומר פועלים נשבעים לחנוני. Rebbe omer
po'alim nishba'im l'chanvani.
The workers should swear to the חנוני, chanvani, not to the בעל
הבית. ba'al habayit. ואי איתא לבעל הבית מיבעי ליה, v'ei ita l'ba'al
habayit mibayei lei, if they would swear to the בעל הבית, ba'al
habayit, it would have to mention it. So אמר רבא פועלים נשבעים
לבעל הבית. amar Rava po'alim nishba'im l'ba'al habayit.
According to רבא, Rava, the workers would swear to the בעל הבית,
ba'al habayit, like in our משנה, במעמד חנוני b'ma'amad chanvani
while the חנוני chanvani is there, but the חנוני chanvani himself will
not take a שבועה. shvu'ah That is, we change the הלכה halacha
from the משנה because we're concerned about people taking שבועת שוא. shvu'at
shav. So who do we make swear? Do we make the פועלים
po'alim swear, do we make the חנוני chanvani swear? Who do we
make swear to whom? All these different opinions.
And then the חנוני chanvani couldn't, well, the חנוני chanvani could be
the בעל הבית, ba'al habayit, right?
No, because then we wouldn't have three parties. The point of this
is that there are three parties. The חנוני chanvani wrote down on
his thing that I have to pay these workers this much cash,
and the בעל הבית ba'al habayit is going to come later and
give him the money. And the point is, so the חנוני chanvani
says, oh, I already paid the money, give me the money. And
the workers say, we never got the money from the חנוני, chanvani,
pay us directly. And so now, the בעל הבית ba'al habayit is
going to have to pay both of them. So the problem,
and each of them will have to take the שבועה shvu'ah? to
collect. So what we want to avoid, even if the בעל הבית
ba'al habayit is losing money, we want to avoid
שבועת שוא, shvu'at shav, because we take שבועות shvu'ot? seriously. We don't
want people swearing falsely. So is there a way to reorganize the
case to eliminate a possibility of some of the possibility of שבועת
שוא shvu'at shav so we don't have two contradictory שבועות? Can we
make only one of the parties involved take a שבועה? shvua So
we had
first a ברייתא, braita, תניא רבי אומר פועלים נשבעים לחנוני. tanya Rebbe
omer po'alim nishba'im l'chanvani. The workers should swear to the חנוני chanvani
that they claim they never collected the money, and then they can
get the money from him. That's one solution, רבי opinion. ואי איתא
לבעל הבית, v'ei ita l'ba'al habayit, basically,
so the חנוני chanvani is completely out because he doesn't then get
to swear to the בעל הבית.
ba'al habayit. Right, because he wouldn't get to swear to the בעל
הבית. ba'al habayit. So that's the objection. So then אמר רבא פועלים
נשבעים לבעל הבית. amar Rava po'alim nishba'im l'ba'al habayit. So according to
רבא, Rava, the workers should swear to the בעל הבית ba'al habayit
במעמד חנוני. b'ma'amad chanvani. While the חנוני chanvani is there, they swear
to the בעל הבית ba'al habayit that they never got paid and
the בעל הבית ba'al habayit will pay them, but the חנוני chanvani
won't be able to make a similar oath. כי היכי דליכסוף מיניה,
ki heichi d'lichsof minei, במעמד חנוני, b'ma'amad chanvani, so
because the presence of the חנוני chanvani will hopefully intimidate them somewhat
to, to tell the truth. So איתמר שתי כיתי עדים המכחישות זו
את זו. itmar shtei kitei eidim hamachishot zo et zo. Now we
can use this case, the case of חנוני על פנקסו, to introduce
a much broader case of interest: two sets of witnesses who contradict.
שתי כיתי עדים המכחישות זו את זו. shtei kitei eidim hamachishot zo
et zo. Two people testify
someone owes one hundred dollars here and somebody testifies and says that
they, well, maybe that's a bad example.
kind of think of a good case.
Yeah, ראובן Reuven killed שמעון Shimon or ראובן Reuven killed לוי Levi
or שמעון killed לוי Levi or something like that. Who was the
murderer, something like that.
Okay, but a monetary case would be easier. I'm trying to think
of a monetary case where where it doesn't where they're not codependent.
Maybe like
the case before about the storekeeper?
Sounds like we'd go by רבא. Rava. פועלים נשבעים לבעל הבית והחנווני
כי היכי דלא חסיף מיניה. Poalim nishbaim labaal habayis v'hachanvani ki heichi
d'lo chasif minei.
That the workers would
swear to the owner...
No, the חנווני chanvani doesn't swear, only the worker swears. The חנווני
chanvani won't end up swearing because of בן ננס Ben Nanas and
רבי's objection. What about that? בן ננס Ben Nanas is an earlier
תנא who disputes his statement and holds that the workers and the
storekeeper may both swear and collect their dues from the householder. However,
it's true that they do not take a full oath, which what
we're worried about. The workers must swear in the presence of the
storekeeper who knows the truth. So they both do swear.
So maybe oh they both swear but we make them take the
שבועה with the presence of the חנווני. chanvani. Okay, so I I
read it wrong. I'm sorry. Okay. So now we like go back
to the גמרא. Gemara. איתמר שתי כיתי עדים מכחישות זו את זו,
Itamar shtei kitei edim machishos zo es zo, two sets of witnesses
contradict each other. אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, זו באה בפני
עצמה ומעידה וזו באה בפני עצמה ומעידה. zo baah bifnei atzmah u'maidah
v'zo baah bifnei atzmah u'maidah. That's why the murder case is a
bad example,
because I would want it to be a monetary case. But basically
the point is each of them would be believed independently even if
they contradict. So this set of witnesses should come and testify, this
set of witnesses should come and testify. רב חסדא אמר, Rav Chisda
amar,
in in the case this just stays in limbo basically.
No, mean or we resolve both cases because each case
of ספק sfeik independently we could think of. Oh, I don't have
an eraser. That's why there's so much stuff on the board. Okay,
this reminds me as well of the the case of שתי שבילים.
shtei shvilim. Oh it's time for שחרית. Shacharis. Let's stop here. Okay,
Rabbi Linzer will do this tomorrow.